<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://aidanacquah.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://aidanacquah.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-04T16:17:44+00:00</updated><id>https://aidanacquah.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A webiste for Aidan Acquah. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Expectation vs. Reality</title><link href="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2024/expectation_reality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Expectation vs. Reality"/><published>2024-09-17T12:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T12:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2024/expectation_reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2024/expectation_reality/"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s address the elephant in the room. It’s been over a year since my last blog post, and frankly, I’d forgotten this repository even existed. What began as an exciting pet project quickly became like that toy you rediscover under the bed a year later, realising only then that it had gone missing.</p> <p>I have no one to blame but myself for this lapse, and it’s worth reflecting on how my expectations for this project differed so sharply from reality. Hopefully, there are lessons to be learned going forward.</p> <h2 id="expectations">Expectations</h2> <p>When I started this repository, my goals were straightforward. I envisioned it as a modern alternative to the traditional CV, a portfolio that would introduce me and my ideas to potential employers. Standard CVs—those endless Word or PDF documents—are prone to versioning chaos with every minor update. They also tend to paint a very one-dimensional picture, focusing solely on work and educational achievements.</p> <p>I imagined this project as a refreshing take on the CV, offering employers a more personal, engaging view of me. I thought that perhaps this could stand out from the norm and that some companies might appreciate the uniqueness of the approach.</p> <p>To achieve this, alongside a conventional CV, I planned to create an About page and a series of blog posts on topics that were top-of-mind each week or month. In terms of design, I had a vague but optimistic vision—something visually appealing but simple. My previous experience with front-end web development suggested that some basic CSS styling and a warm colour palette could provide a professional yet personal feel. Markdown and Jekyll seemed the perfect combo—easy integration with GitHub Pages, allowing new posts with minimal effort.</p> <h2 id="reality">Reality</h2> <p>Some of those ambitions did materialise. I managed to set up and deploy the pages, and the links all worked without much fuss. Navigation between pages is smooth, and when I needed to access my CV for job applications, it was readily available—no searching through endless versions to find the most up-to-date copy.</p> <p>The catch is, the only tasks that got completed were the ones I could tackle in one sitting. Anything requiring continuous refinement or attention? Those were left by the wayside.</p> <p>The biggest disappointment has been the styling. Right now, it looks… well, let’s just say it’s far from where I imagined. It’s a problem that can definitely be fixed, but it requires more time and energy than I initially budgeted for. As a result, the site sits in a half-baked state that doesn’t motivate me to keep working on it.</p> <p>Another lesson learned: expecting to churn out blog posts regularly while juggling a PhD and other priorities was overly ambitious. Without making this project a priority or setting up reminders, posting a new blog each week turned out to be wishful thinking.</p> <h2 id="moving-forward">Moving Forward</h2> <p>Maybe it’s okay that I lost momentum with this project. After all, I’ve come back to it, and it still serves its intended purpose. But moving forward, the first order of business is fixing the design. I need to get the page into a state that I’m comfortable sharing with others—especially with potential employers. Once that’s done, I can turn my attention to further improvements.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="phd-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let’s address the elephant in the room. It’s been over a year since my last blog post, and frankly, I’d forgotten this repository even existed. What began as an exciting pet project quickly became like that toy you rediscover under the bed a year later, realising only then that it had gone missing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Academia vs Industry</title><link href="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/academia_industry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Academia vs Industry"/><published>2023-08-11T12:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-11T12:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/academia_industry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/academia_industry/"><![CDATA[<p>As I approach the final year of my PhD, the looming question grows nearer: Academia or Industry? For some, the answer is obvious, as their inclination has always directed them toward one or the other. But for me, the answer remains unclear, and it’s a question I’ve been seeking to answer.</p> <p>It’s crystal clear to me that I wish to be a researcher. From a young age, I told my parents that I wanted to be an inventor. My younger self would conjure up ridiculous invention ideas, sometimes letting my imagination run wild with elaborate concepts that were hardly practical, and my passion for them would wane as new interests emerged. After several years of high school, the time came to choose a university course, and engineering seemed closest to my dream. Concepts like brain-controlled limbs and interactive assistive devices seemed to embody the future of engineering, and I aspired to be at the forefront of these innovations.</p> <p>However, university proved to be a reality check for my fantasies. While I didn’t excel in robotics or mechanics, I found enjoyment in more software-related engineering projects, particularly in modeling, data processing, and data analytics. After gaining work experience in software development, returning to academia for research in data science, and participating in a data science industry placement, I’m convinced that research is the arena where I can fulfill my dream.</p> <p>In many industries, research is predominantly associated with academia. The core of new scientific developments often originates from proof-of-concept projects initiated in academic settings. Recent examples include the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRISPR_gene_editing">CRISPR gene editing technology</a> and the discovery of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave">gravitational waves</a> — both began as academic research endeavors before finding practical applications in various industries.</p> <p>However, in the realm of data science, research projects often find their origins in industry and are subsequently validated or reproduced in academia. Examples such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recommender_system">recommendation systems</a> by companies like Amazon and Netflix, as well as advancements in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_language_processing">natural language processing</a> by Apple’s Siri, Google Assistant, and Amazon’s Alexa, highlight this trend. Many academics in this field acknowledge that industry research often outpaces academic research, which makes academia appear less desirable from my perspective.</p> <p>Over-expectation is a significant risk associated with industry-driven research, more so than in academia. Many research projects demand substantial investments of time and money, with the anticipation of novel outcomes. Companies often conduct research with the primary goal of generating profits from the applications of their findings. For instance, if a company invests in researching a new product, they expect the research to demonstrate the product’s success, enabling them to sell it for profit. This can introduce bias into the research process and impose tight deadlines that may compromise the research quality. Academia, on the other hand, doesn’t face these same pressures, though some departments struggle to strike a balance between numerous publications and a few high-impact ones, requiring careful management.</p> <p>Contracts in academia tend to be shorter, offer lower salaries, and provide fewer bonus packages compared to the industry. This gap is particularly noticeable in the tech sector, one of today’s most prosperous industries. A data science researcher position at a prestigious UK university would more closely match the salaries of similarly experienced researchers in completely unrelated industries rather than those in industry research. Consequently, industry offers often come with salaries nearly double that of academia. Moreover, academic contracts frequently span 1 to 3 years, even for critical members of research groups, providing poor long-term stability. The longer contracts in industry also allow for better career planning and trajectory.</p> <p>Research in academia promotes transparency and the sharing of knowledge with the broader community. This aspect becomes especially pertinent in the data science industry, which is currently embroiled in a transformative debate over whether research-related code should be openly accessible. Beyond this, the dissemination of learning through teaching is essential to the research spirit and lies at the heart of academia. As someone passionate about sharing knowledge, I aspire to work in a role that enables me to do so, reaching beyond just my immediate colleagues.</p> <p>In summary, the decision to pursue a career in research within academia or industry is a challenging one, and it’s a decision I continue to grapple with. At the core of this choice, I must strike a balance between factors such as stability, interest, and passion. My hope is that I’ll eventually find a place that offers an ideal equilibrium of these considerations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="phd-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As I approach the final year of my PhD, the looming question grows nearer: Academia or Industry? For some, the answer is obvious, as their inclination has always directed them toward one or the other. But for me, the answer remains unclear, and it’s a question I’ve been seeking to answer.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Media and Privacy</title><link href="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/privacy_and_social_media/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Media and Privacy"/><published>2023-08-08T12:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-08T12:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/privacy_and_social_media</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aidanacquah.github.io/blog/2023/privacy_and_social_media/"><![CDATA[<p>In 2020, Netflix released a documentary called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Social_Dilemma">“The Social Dilemma”</a> that addressed concerns about the widespread adoption of social media and its potential negative consequences. This skepticism toward social media had been growing, especially following the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal">Cambridge Analytica scandal</a>. This scandal revealed that Facebook data had been misused by Cambridge Analytica to manipulate various elections. Despite the rapid normalization of social media worldwide, its effects are only beginning to be fully realized.</p> <h2 id="positive-feelings-about-social-media">Positive Feelings about Social Media</h2> <p>It might surprise you to know that I don’t despise all forms of social media. For instance, WhatsApp has undeniably improved the lives of many. In my earlier years, connecting with family abroad was a costly and challenging endeavor. Today, it’s as simple as communicating with someone nearby. Similarly, platforms like Reddit and YouTube serve as valuable sources of information and news for a wider audience.</p> <p>Various social media platforms connect people based on shared interests, such as fandoms and social groups. These platforms have also facilitated the formation and maintenance of friendships, across continents.</p> <h2 id="negative-feelings-about-social-media">Negative Feelings about Social Media</h2> <p>We must also acknowledge the shortcomings and failures of social media. Some of these failures stem from how people use social media, while others originate from design flaws.</p> <p>Billion dollar social media companies like Meta and Alphabet are incentivized to keep people on their platforms by feeding a curated source of information. This encouragement of addiction, combined with the constant need to provide superficial updates, creates a false sense of communication.</p> <p>Moreover, the pressure to conform to social norms leads to a feeling of social pressure to use social media. This pressure can even result in the erosion of authentic communication, substituting it with shallow interactions.</p> <p>Privacy, a crucial aspect of personal well-being, is also significantly compromised in the realm of social media. The collection and exploitation of personal data have raised serious concerns about user privacy and the potential misuse of information.</p> <h2 id="personal-experience-with-social-media">Personal Experience with Social Media</h2> <p>My personal journey with social media has been relatively limited. During my late primary school years, using platforms like MSN Messenger was the norm among friends during summer holidays. Although it was a precursor to modern messaging apps, the process felt clunky compared to today’s smartphone-driven experience.</p> <p>Over the years, Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram dominated the social media landscape. Even before smartphones were widespread, these platforms began shaping our lives. At the age of 14, I was already sharing photos, updating statuses, and building connections on Facebook. Twitter’s limited character count encouraged divisive content, amplifying negative aspects of communication.</p> <p>By the time I turned 18, I realized I wasn’t comfortable with the extent of my social media presence. Yet, avoiding social media was becoming synonymous with disengaging from society. Facebook and similar platforms had become central to social interactions, and “ghosting” emerged as a term for those who were unreachable on social media.</p> <p>Today, while I maintain some accounts, I avoid active participation on platforms like Facebook, Instagram, and Twitter. I use WhatsApp to communicate globally, and I consume media on YouTube and Reddit without actively contributing. Platforms like Threads and TikTok remain unexplored by me.</p> <h2 id="hierarchy-of-social-media-usage">Hierarchy of Social Media Usage</h2> <p>In my view, there’s a hierarchy of concern for groupings of social media usage.</p> <p>The lowest level includes messaging services like WhatsApp, Skype, Signal, and Discord. These are of lowest concern to me, as they enable further communication, while not trying to completely replace all social interaction.</p> <p>Next come media providers like YouTube, Twitch, and Reddit. Most people can find healthy ways to engage with this, by timeboxing their usage, and limiting the engagement in commentary. The rise of echo chambers within these communities is also a concern, which to today appears difficult to address.</p> <p>Finally, at the highest level, we have social network services like Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, and TikTok. It’s these social network services that raise the most concerns. For these platforms, additional steps must be taken to ensure limited publication of personal information, and restricted use of accounts.</p> <p>I’ve shared these thoughts because, much like hosting my website on GitHub, I encounter similar privacy concerns to social network platforms. I don’t possess all the answers to these issues, but I believe it’s valuable to reflect on them openly. My perspective might evolve over time. For now, having this content on my terms gives me a sense of control while maintaining a certain level of privacy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="phd-thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 2020, Netflix released a documentary called “The Social Dilemma” that addressed concerns about the widespread adoption of social media and its potential negative consequences. This skepticism toward social media had been growing, especially following the Cambridge Analytica scandal. This scandal revealed that Facebook data had been misused by Cambridge Analytica to manipulate various elections. Despite the rapid normalization of social media worldwide, its effects are only beginning to be fully realized.]]></summary></entry></feed>